This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Developers, are you ready?
It's time to upgrade your data platform
to InterSystems IRIS.
Choose your language. Choose your tools.
Choose your environment. Collaborate,
build faster, and deploy more
efficiently.
When you can make faster decisions,
there's no telling what you'll create.
Ready, set, code.
Start coding for free. Visit
intersystems.com/try
to try IRIS.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host, Jeff Doolittle.
In this episode, I am pleased to welcome
world-renowned software architect and
author Juval Löwy to discuss his
recently published book, Writing
Software.
Juval, founder of IDesign, is a master
software architect specializing in
system and project design.
He has helped countless companies around
the world deliver quality software on
schedule and on budget.
Recognized by Microsoft as one of the
world's top experts and industry
leaders, he participated in internal
strategic design reviews for C#, WCF,
and related technologies,
and was named a software legend.
He has published several bestsellers and
numerous articles on almost every aspect
of modern software development.
Löwy speaks frequently at major
international software development
conferences
and conducts master classes around the
world, teaching thousands of
professionals the skills required of
modern software architects and how to
take an active role as design, process,
and technology leaders.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio,
Yuhal. My distinct pleasure, Jeff.
Your book is titled Writing Software,
but it's spelled r i g h t i n g rather
than w r i t i n g. Can you explain the
word play and the reason for the title?
And so, the aim of the book is to write
the broken industry that we have, the
software industry.
As I write in the preface for the book,
almost every aspect of software
development is actually broken.
And what I aim in the book is not just
write the industry, but hopefully
uh be the launching pad or bring about a
software development renaissance.
That reminds me of a claim that you make
in the beginning of the book when you
say specifically the software industry
as a whole is in a deep crisis. So,
perhaps you can expound a little bit on
the nature and causes of this crisis, as
you put it.
Well, it's easy to explain the elements
of the crisis. It's deeper to explain
the causes.
So, if you look at
how we develop software today, every
aspect, every element of software
development is broken. Let's look at
cost. Software costs too much.
Now, when you say something costs too
much, it's a relative term. With respect
to what? Well, the only way to quantify
it is is with respect to the benefit to
the customer.
And we're past the point of diminishing
returns in software development.
For example, almost everybody that uses
Office 365 or 2019 would have been just
fine with Office 2010 or 2013.
Why? Because it was just good enough.
But 2013 costs the same as 2010, and
2016 costs the same as 2010, and so on.
So, you're just sending money for
nothing for these vendors. When in fact,
the old software, if it was done right,
it's just good enough.
In addition, the cost of software is not
just the cost of writing the bits. It's
the overall cost of ownership. And if
you were to actually account for it
correctly across 7 10 years and multiple
versions,
the cost would actually be prohibitively
expensive.
In addition, the cost of doing changes
to software is so much that every once
in a while when a customer or manager
asks developer to do something, they
throw their hands in air and say, "We
cannot do that."
Now, cannot is a statement of
feasibility. Well, in fact, if it's just
code, you can write different code.
But when they're saying we cannot do
that, they're actually doing a statement
of cost because they're saying, "Of
course we can do it, but the cost of
doing it is going to be so prohibitive,
it's going to be cheaper to just wipe
the slate clean and do this whole thing
again from scratch and do this one thing
you're trying to do here." Which means
the cost of what they're trying to do
here is expensive.
And then,
there's time. Time means nothing for
software developers.
Deadlines for most developers are these
useless things wishing by as they are
chained to their desks.
In fact, you you laugh, it's actually
sad. If developers meet the deadline,
everybody's going to be surprised
because the expectation is for them to
fail.
And
how can you run a business and be viable
in a world where time and money do not
matter? I mean, you couldn't operate a
hot dog stand this way.
That makes sense. Then there's
requirements. Developers solve the wrong
problems. In fact, developers routinely
fail to communicate with customers. If
customers give developers
the correct requirements, everybody's
going to be surprised again.
Which on its own is is a whole other
enigma because
if it's only a surprise the customers
give you the wrong requirements, why
does everybody fail to accommodate the
failure to communicate with the
customer, which is a whole separate
question and why did they fail to
communicate with the customer? And
side-by-side with unmet requirements and
disappointment, there's requirements
that are perfectly communicated but
developers simply decide not to do
because it's it's too expensive or it
takes too long or they just don't know.
And it it's really puzzling how nobody
takes into effect how the introduction
of the system would actually change the
requirements against which it is written
in the first place. Then there's
staffing. Often not the same people that
write the code maintain it over years
and the people that maintain it simply
cannot make sense
of the software.
Most software teams have
crossed the threshold
of being able to make sense of the
complexity of their own system. And so
the system is completely unmaintainable
and they try and solve problems or
introduce an improvement and they
introduce new problems and new defects.
And it's of course now it's some kind of
a runaway reaction where uh you
introduce one problem, it's all one
problem, introduce two additional ones
and so on. And that just grinds people
to nothing and then we have uh high
attrition and burnout. And this just
uh heaved on people to the point that
the stress level is so high, you see
developers actually getting sick from
work.
And then there's of course quality. I
mean, in software
the word
bug is synonymous with software. And
it's it's it's almost where hey, I have
a little bug over here. No, it's a
hideous monster defect. I mean, even a
little bug in a sensor can take down a
whole jumbo jet apparently. There there
are no little bugs. I mean, what
nonsense it is to try and classify bugs.
And if I were to tell the listeners that
every project I was ever involved in, I
shipped on schedule, on budget, with
zero defects,
I'm not quite sure which part of that
statement would offend them more, but I
suspect it's the fact that I shipped
with zero defects because in their mind
it is absolutely impossible
to have impeccable software. And to make
it even worse, none of these problems is
actually new. People now spend their
entire career in software land not
seeing software done right even once.
And so now something else has happened.
They think that
it's just impossible to have any other
level of existence.
And so if you try and actually even
improve things or suggest things,
if they have already concluded it's
impossible to do any better, you know,
start insulting their own intelligence
or they start fighting you as you try
and actually improve things.
So the status quo must be the way it has
to be.
The way it has to be. It's That's why
I'm saying that this is a crisis. Every
aspect of software development is
actually broken. Mhm. And it's not just
me saying that. Go to Google and type
software projects success or failure
rate and you're going to see horrendous
horrendous statistics.
Most software projects actually fail.
They fail to meet the objectives, their
commitments.
Uh the ratio of project that fail is
higher than project that succeed and
even that is a misleading statement
because
the situation is so bad,
companies and organization
had to change the definition of success
because if you can't clean up your act,
either you you clean up your act or you
lower the bar. And so success in
software today is defined as anything
that doesn't bank up the company right
now. You can fix it later.
Your mistakes can destroy lives 10 years
from now, but if some code leaves the
building missing a leg with a black eye,
well, that's actually okay.
That's considered success.
And so it is next to impossible to find
projects today that are done correctly
start to finish. So how would you
respond to the person who might say, "I
agree that there are elements of a
crisis, but the company that I'm working
for is actually doing quite well and
making significant margins and we aren't
experiencing the crisis the way that you
describe it. How might you approach
someone like that and and maybe what
would identify the fact that they
actually are in crisis, perhaps they
don't realize it, which I think is kind
of what you're you're expressing.
Scott Adams this is what Scott Adams
recently dubbed loser think, meaning in
one word it's a thinking of a loser.
It's he coined that term and the reason
it's loser think is because first of all
you can't say, "I'm doing well."
You could have done much better and you
lost a lot of money. That's that's
something that's that is probably
implied.
Sort of the what the the what is seen
and what isn't unseen.
The dog that didn't bark and all of
that, but it's more for fun than that.
We do software today as if it's the dark
ages, meaning if you look at the dark
ages, most people had ugly, brutal,
filthy, short lives. But you know what?
They still had a good time and they
raised families, they had parties and
they laughed, right? Now, even in the
dark ages, you had people that were way
better off than other people. I mean
look at the warlord in the 10th century
with the feast and the servants and all
of that, right? You can say, "I'm at the
top of the world. I am the king. I'm the
best."
And
the problem is it's it's all true by the
way and you're very successful. The
problem is you're still a 10th century
warlord.
If you have to choose between being just
a nobody in the 21st century or a 10th
century warlord, I think you would
choose the warm bath once a day and
Instagram than being a 10th century
warlord. So, saying that you're at the
top of the world and you're successful
in a pitiful environment is absolutely
the statement of a loser.
And maybe somebody who's not really
caring about the state of the industry
in general, but is content to
take what's good for them. Perhaps.
Well,
I'm very much in the Adam Smith camp
that people should be egoistic and
egocentric and if everybody act towards
their own interest, eventually the
invisible hand make sure that there's
prosperity for all, okay? So, I'm not
I'm not that much that people say,
"Okay, let's just fix the world."
Especially you can't aspire to fix up
the world and like the whole industry if
your room is messy, right? I mean, to me
it's just hypocrisy people saying we
should do this and we should do that and
society should do this when in fact the
house is a big mess, you know? Clean up
your room before you pontificate for
others how to do their job. If it isn't
working at home, don't export it. Yeah,
for example, yes.
Okay. So, that's I think a good summary
of the nature of the crisis.
Well, hopefully there's an answer for
how the crisis can be addressed and I
have a feeling you have some opinions
about what those solutions might be.
So, if you abstract away the specifics
of quality and schedule and budget and
maintainability and so on, at the root
cause is a poor design. It's a poor
design of the software system. It's a
poor design of the project that was used
to build it. It's a poor design of the
team, of the allocation of the people,
of the way you build the system. All of
that is poorly designed.
And what I propose in the book is a way
or a methodology of fixing it. Now, it's
not a silver bullet because there are no
silver bullet. In fact, all the ideas in
the book require a lot of practice
and a lot of devotion to actually get
right. But, it's also not just a one
thing I'm proposing in the book and the
reason is if you have a
multi-dimensional crisis,
you need a multi-dimensional solution.
You You can't just fix one aspect. You
can't just fix the the design of the
system and then everything else would be
fine. It doesn't work this way. Even if
you have the best system design and
architecture,
if the project doesn't have enough time
or money to build it or the developers
cannot build it, you will fail.
Right? so everything has to be aligned
for success.
What you're recommending then sounds
like an integrated and holistic approach
to the software crisis.
The word integration and holistic is is
is a good step. I look at it as a
formula,
meaning to fix the software industry,
you need to fix both the system aspects
and the project aspect. So, you design
system, you design projects, and along
the way we also design your own career
and your teams, and all of that would
fall into place as well.
I want to focus the remainder of our
conversation specifically on system
design so that we can give our listeners
a sense of what your proposals are
for designing systems.
Where would you like to start that
exploration? What's the the most
important element
I guess the most important thing is to
discuss what not to do.
Okay.
And the reason we have to start there
is because the what not to do is the
prevailing modus operandi of designing
software systems today.
I'll be blunt, unless somebody has spent
some time with me, they're doing it
wrong. Almost every system I've seen in
the wild
is designed incorrectly. And so, I guess
the most important thing that we should
discuss is that you should
avoid what I call functional
decomposition. So, let's just
explain those three words. Architecture
in general is an act of decomposition.
You take a big nebulous idea and you
break it down into smaller building
blocks, components, services, whatever
the methodology or the abstraction level
is.
That makes sense.
Most people do functional decomposition.
Functional decomposition means you look
at the required functionality of the
system
and you decompose accordingly. You
reflect in the architecture the required
functionality. So, if I give a
requirement spec
that reads 1.2.3 system should do 4.5.6
system should do B, you would have an A
block, a B block, a C block.
That is the kiss of death. If if you did
that, the project is already failed,
past tense. The project is already
failed before anybody wrote the first
line of code.
And why is that? So, how much time do we
have?
So, I'll give you I'll give you a few
reasons why this is bad. If every one of
them is literally a nail in the coffin
to kill it.
But, I'll save the best nail for last so
we can discuss it in the light of what
is the right way of doing things.
So,
first, you're not going to get just
three things to do. A decent size
software system today may have a
hundred, two hundred, three hundred
things to do.
If you do true functional decomposition,
you're going to have an architecture
with 300 blocks.
Now, 300 blocks is really, really the
epitome of a bad design. And the reason
is, well, each block is small, doable,
understandable. The integration cost of
such an architecture is astronomical.
Absolutely.
And so, we're talking about level of
complexity that defy the mind. Now, you
could do something else. You can have a
component or a service and pump into it
the A and the B and the C and the D. And
you have these ugly dumping ground of
functionalities, and you get these crazy
monoliths of dooms. You can have two or
three of them side by side sometimes.
And the problem is that, well, you don't
have the integration cost of an
explosion of little things, the internal
complexity of those big things is also
astronomical because complexity is not
linear to size. Something twice as big
is not twice as complex, it's four times
as complex, 20 times as complex, and so
on.
So,
the functional decomposition always
lands you in these extreme areas of
complexity that nobody can understand
the intricate relationship between and
inside and across components of your
architecture. And if you don't
understand your architecture, nobody can
maintain it, extend it, reuse it. The
other problem with functional
decomposition is that somebody has to
say to the system,
"Do functionality A, do B, do billing,
invoicing, shipping, whatever it is."
And that somebody is the client of the
system. But the notion that you need to
do A and then B and then C is business
logic.
So now all of a sudden,
the client is infused infuses business
logic. The client has to know that you
can't do billing if you haven't done
invoicing.
Now every developer knows
that you should never pollute the client
code with business logic.
And yet, they're all doing it. And the
reason is functional decomposition
forces them
to pollute the client with business
logic.
So now two things happen. First, the
last thing you want is to maintain the
business logic in two places, in the
system and in the clients. And since you
have to put it in the client, you tend
to beef up the clients and dumb down the
system. So now you end up with the
clients being the system and some kind
of a poor excuse or hand-waving for
so-called service.
Makes sense.
The other problem is,
what does it take to add a new client?
So marketing walks us into the office
and say, "We need to add a mobile
device."
The problem is, it's not just adding
another client, it's a duplication of
the system. And I have to maintain the
business logic in two places and it's
not going to be exactly the same
business logic because of slight
differences between the clients. And
then you have to add the third type and
a fourth type of a client. At some
point, developers throw their hands in
the air and say, "We cannot take it
anymore. No more clients."
The other problem is that because of the
interaction between these areas of
functionality, suppose I have another
system that needs to do just a
particular functionality, just B, just
billing.
If you lift the B from one system, you
can never drop it in another system
because the A and the C is hanging off
it because before the B you do an A and
after the B you do a C. And the reason
is functional decomposition is always
time decomposition as well. You
decompose based on a particular order.
As a result, reuse does not exist in the
function decompose system. Another
problem is that as you enter the system
to do the A, back to the client, B, back
to the client, C, back to the client,
you enter the system in three places.
And that means three places to worry
about security, and three places to
worry about scalability, performance,
availability, responsiveness,
redundancy, throughput, performance.
Everybody knows that a good design
ideally would have a single point of
entry, but should certainly minimize the
number of points of entry. Function
decomposition always tends to maximize
the points of entry.
And with it, of course, complexity,
because now you start smearing security
and scalability, of course, all places
in your architecture. Hm. So, points of
entry are maximized, coupling sounds
like it's maximized, and business logic
gets spread out across the system,
particularly in the clients. And
complexity is maximized, right? Because
of the interaction and the internal
complexity.
But you know what you know what, Jeff, I
can prove to you that function
decomposition is the wrong way of
designing system without using a single
software argument.
Okay, great.
I'm going to use the first law of
thermodynamics.
The first law of thermodynamics simply
states that you cannot add value without
sweating.
Now, we don't know quite why this is the
first law of thermodynamics. There's
nothing in Newtonian physics that says
it has to be so. But it is.
But it is. We know at least that on this
side of the Big Bang that's where things
are. We're not quite sure what happened
before the Big Bang, but on this side of
the Big Bang
the first law of thermodynamics rules
the universe.
And
everybody knows that you cannot have a
free lunch. I mean, that's another way
of saying there's
no way of adding value without sweating.
Now,
if you look at architecture,
architecture is a high added value
activity. Everybody is listening to us
instead of doing something else because
they value architecture.
In theory, being able to have a system
that's maintainable for long period of
time that minimizes total cost of
ownership, that is extensible, reusable,
secure, these are all high added value
aspects.
Now, functional decomposition is fairly
easy. If you have a list either in a
requirement spec or on a scrum board of
all the required functionalities,
the architecture is
simple. No sweat, you say. I have an A
block, a B block, a C block.
But that's the problem. You said no
sweat. Now, you try
and cheat the first law of
thermodynamics because on one hand you
endeavor to add value, on the other
hand, you endeavor to do it without
sweating.
And according to the nature of our
universe, this is just not going to
happen.
And so, here I just proved to you that
without a single software argument,
you should never do functional
decomposition.
And yet, that is exactly what almost
everybody is doing.
So, as you're describing this, this
sounds like a horrible way of doing
things. So, why would anyone do things
this way
if it causes so many problems?
The answer is very simple, human nature.
Human beings cannot resist the allure of
the free lunch.
And this has nothing to do with
software, right? I mean, let's look at
the simple example. Let's look at
alchemy.
For thousands of years, people tried to
turn lead into gold.
It didn't work even once, and yet they
commanded kings and so on. They were the
smartest people in every kingdom, and
every alchemist had their own unique way
of mixing the potions and saying the
incantations and so on.
Zero results, and for thousands of
years, the best practice was to keep
trying this. Why? The allure of the free
lunch. It's in our nature to do this.
And And unfortunately, this is nothing
to do with intelligence.
The greatest alchemist of all time was
Isaac Newton.
And
most people are less smart than Isaac
Newton. And yet Isaac Newton was an
alchemist. He kept trying to find the
philosopher's stone and so on. And so it
takes iron will to overcome the desire
to do functional decomposition. And
that's actually the challenge in doing
it.
And in doing what we're going to
discuss, hopefully, how to write with
doing it, because everybody around you
are going to be hell-bent on doing it
incorrectly. But, you know, given the
nature of the crisis in software, you
basically be fighting insanity here,
because the smartest man that ever lived
said that the definition of insanity is
doing things more of the same, but
expecting better results.
And I I expect the customer and the boss
to want you to do things better. I mean,
arguably, if you're doing a new system,
the reason you're doing it is because
the old system didn't work. Because you
should be able to maintain your systems
for decades.
And yet, you can't. And therefore, you
need to do something else, which is
hopefully better. But, how could you
better do better by doing more of the
same, right? And so, Einstein said,
"That's the definition of insanity."
And so, you will have to fight the
lunatics trying, again, to do functional
decomposition. Yeah, and that's
interesting when you mentioned it's not
necessarily a measure of intelligence,
it's just a measure of human behavior to
do things the same way over and over
again. That's right.
And that being said, there must be a
solution to this problem. And I have a
feeling you have one in mind.
Yes, there is.
What I propose architects should do is
decompose based on volatility.
Decompose based on volatility means
architects should identify areas of
potential change, things that could
change in the system. And those you
encapsulate in building blocks of the
system.
And then you provide the required
behavior of the system as interaction
between these encapsulated areas of
volatility. Decomposing based on
volatility is literally the essence of a
good design. All system around us are
designed using this principle. And the
reason is when you start thinking about
volatility based decomposition, you
start envisioning your system as a
series of vaults.
Each vault encapsulate some area of
volatility.
Now, when a change happen, the change is
very dangerous. It's like a hand grenade
and yet you open up the door of the
appropriate vault, toss the hand grenade
inside,
and close the vault. And the vault does
boof.
And whatever was inside the vault may be
complicit completely destroyed,
and yet there's no sharpness flying all
over the place destroying everything
else in the system.
And put differently, you've contained
the change. Now, if you look at
functional decomposition,
functional decomposition would maximize
the impact of such a change because you
decompose based on functionality,
by definition, the change can never be
in one place because your building
blocks are associated with
functionality, not with change or
volatility. So, now when a change
happens, it is like tossing a hand
grenade into your system and everything
is torn apart.
And that is the
real reason why functional decomposition
is so deadly. All the other things I
said about it is just to wet your
appetite.
The inability to handle change is the
kiss of death for any software system.
Could you summarize that by saying that
things that change together should live
together in your system?
There's there's another layer here
which we can get into which is
if if you need to design software
systems, you can ask yourself, are there
common areas of volatility in typical
software systems?
And if you can recognize that in advance
and you come up with a nice starting
point for the design effort. But you
could take it even a step further and
you can say,
are the typical interaction and
relationship between these areas of
volatility.
And if you bring that into your design
effort, then you already have some
structure
and you don't have to invent the wheel
every time.
And that is actually the nature of all
good design or all good architectures,
that there is this very high level of
recurring of self-similarity. So, I
wouldn't actually say live together, I
would say that you should actually look
for high degrees of symmetry and high
degrees
of recurring architecture. Now, we're
not talking about the actual details.
For example,
a mouse and an elephant have the same
architecture. You agree about that? Yes.
But the details are totally different.
And so, and yet if you know that you
need to have
a kidney, a liver,
two lungs, and so on, then you're
already very much on your way to
designing a small little animal or big
animal, right?
And so, that's another thing that I
discuss actually in the book. I discuss
structure you can actually put on top of
software systems, but it's all driven by
the idea of decomposing based on
volatility, that you identify the
volatilities,
and then if you identify certain types
of volatilities, they have these kind of
structures in your architecture and
they're allowed to do this set of
interactions.
Calling all developers.
There's no telling what you can create
when you upgrade your data platform to
InterSystems IRIS.
Are you ready to build the applications
you want, however you want them? Are you
ready to develop applications faster
than ever? Collaborate, build faster,
and deploy more efficiently. Tomorrow's
next breakthroughs are waiting for you
today. InterSystems IRIS data platform.
Ready, set, code. Start coding for free.
Visit intersystems.com/try
to try IRIS.
What are some
concrete volatilities that might help
our listeners have a better
understanding of what that term means.
So, most software systems
implement some set of required
behaviors.
And note that I didn't say requirements
or functionalities. I said required
behaviors.
It turns out that
even the way most developers and
marketing people phrase requirements is
actually wrong because they use
functional requirements.
Functional requirements talk about the
required functionality of the system.
Well, in fact, what developers should
really uh receive from the customer or
marketing is the required behavior of
the system. How the system is required
to behave.
And the reason you want to focus on the
required behavior is because required
behaviors are less open for
interpretation than required
functionalities. Required functionality,
there's so many ways of doing any
particular functionality. But the
behaviors are much more close-ended
here. You have to do it like this, like
this, like this, and like this. So, you
can think of any required behavior as
some kind of a sequence of activities.
Once you understand that all
requirements should be expressed as
sequence of activities, there's even a
name for it. It's called the use case.
Now, if all use cases are sequences of
activities,
then there's actually inherent
volatility in it because
the sequence could actually change. So,
if I have If I have three activities, A,
B, C, I can do it sequentially, A, B, C.
I can do them all concurrently in
parallel. Now, I'm still doing the same
activities, A, B, C, and yet there's
enormous volatility in the sequence. Or
maybe I'm doing A first and then B and C
sequentially.
Or maybe I'm doing A and then based on a
condition, I'm doing B or C, right? So,
the sequence can be highly volatile
independently from the activities.
And so, whenever you have
this kind of volatility, I recommend you
use a type of uh service I call a
manager which encapsulate the volatility
in the sequence.
Now,
even if you keep the sequence
fixed, you can still change the
activities because I could have a
sequence of A and then B and then C. I
can have a sequence of A and then D and
then C.
So, I can change the activities
independently from the sequence.
And so, volatility in activities,
meaning all the ways of doing a
particular activity, is completely
independent from the volatility
of the sequence.
And so, once you understand that, you
start looking for volatilities in
activities, and I call those things in
my structure and taxonomy engines.
Now, all the business logic in the world
typically operates on some kind of
either state that you maintain or
interacts with other systems that
maintain your state.
And so, there's actually two additional
volatilities here, which is
how you access those resources.
Mhm. I mean, how many ways there are of
accessing a database? 17? I mean, maybe
more and counting, right?
Right.
And even if um
you fix the um the way you access
something, what you access can actually
change because I could access a file or
a cache or a database, and database can
be local or remote or cloud-based.
And so, the resource that you access can
be a queue, can be a database, can be a
cache, is also volatile.
And so,
a whole set of volatilities exist in
resources and also in how you access
those resources.
Separate volatilities exist in clients.
Different clients can have different
rendering technologies they present
information to users or different SDKs
that they expose and different
technologies that they use to expose the
functionality of the underlying system.
Absolutely. So, that also volatility
needs to encapsulate.
A whole family of volatilities is
something I call utilities.
Every decent software system has
infrastructure that it requires to
survive, things like security, message
bus,
queuing, diagnostic, instrumentation,
profiling, logging.
How many ways there are of doing
logging? How many ways there are of
doing security?
And so, the last thing you want to do is
merely say the security volatility that
you cross all your components because
when the security requirements will
change,
all your system would detonate.
And so, you need to have utilities that
encapsulate the infrastructure
volatility, which is nothing to do with
the required behavior of the system.
Hardly any requirement spec contains
specific requirements against the way
you're supposed to do logging, right?
That's internal to the system, but you
have to do it along with diagnostic and
instrumentation and so on. That makes
sense.
And so, once you understand that there
is this recurring patterns of volatility
in software system,
the next thing you can say, okay, are
there typical interactions? Just as
there is typical volatilities, are there
typical interactions? Could you compile
a list of do's, a list of don'ts, a list
of always of how these things interact
with each other?
Now, it's fairly abstract as as I'm
doing it like this, but at the end of
the day, these are universal design
principles. If you open your eyes, you
will see that everything in the world
around you is actually designed this
way. For example, we we are recording
this webcast right now
by integrating areas of encapsulated
volatility. For example,
the laptop I'm using is very different
than your laptop. In fact, it is as
unique as a fingerprint. There isn't a
single laptop like it on the face of the
planet.
And yet, all the volatility is
encapsulated behind the microphone jack
and then the HDMI uh
and the video card. As long as it sends
the video card to the screen and the
audio signal down the wire to you, I
don't really care what happens beyond
it. It's it's completely
different than any other laptop, but
it's encapsulated. I could not conduct
this webcast and podcast if I were to
care about the specifics of these
things, right?
If I look at
uh heart, my heart encapsulates an
enormous amount of volatility of pumping
blood.
You can have high pulse, low pulse,
running, standing, walking, high
adrenaline, low adrenaline, high low
blood pressure, high blood pressure.
And yet, I don't care because that
volatility is encapsulated. I could not
do any of my day-to-day activities if I
cared about the volatility of pumping
blood.
And when you're driving a car, I can
drive your car safely because even
though your car is very different than
mine, that volatility is encapsulated
behind, say, the steering wheel and the
gas pedal and so on.
And by the way, it used to be that these
things were not encapsulated and then it
was really, really difficult to operate
these machines.
Now, the nice thing about it is that I
can actually change
my laptop with no ill effects to my
heart or my car. And And I know it
sounds strange because in most of the
system, that's completely impossible.
And yet, as long as I encapsulate the
volatility of my laptop, my car, and my
heart are actually unaffected. Maybe my
wallet is, but not my heart and my car,
okay? Sure.
And so, all good design
decompose based on volatility, meaning
they encapsulate the inherent volatility
of what is actually going on.
You mentioned podcasting before and the
fact that our laptops are not
particularly made for podcasting and yet
here we are podcasting. So,
can you explain the relationship between
this concept of
encapsulating volatility and how
real-world interactions actually
emerge?
So,
this is actually
one of the key concepts I have in the
writing software. It's an idea
I call composable design. And let me
walk you back
through this kind of fundamental
machinery of what this is actually all
about.
The mission of the architect is to
design a system
that addresses all requirements.
By all requirement, I actually mean all
requirements. I really mean all
requirements.
That sounds daunting.
Present and future, known and unknown.
Nothing less will do.
You can't leave some requirements and
say, "Well, I don't have it because I I
didn't have enough time."
You have to satisfy all requirements.
That's where the bar is set. Nothing
less will do. If you don't do it, then
at some point in the future, the system
is going to implode.
Now,
traditionally, people tried to do it
using some variation of functional
decomposition.
Now, by doing so, what they were
actually doing, they were designing
against the requirements.
When you design against the
requirements, the one thing we know the
requirements do is that they actually
change.
And that's actually a good thing because
if a requirement wouldn't change,
nobody here would actually have a job.
No None of our listeners, neither you
nor me, by the way, would have a job.
Because somebody somehow would write
somewhere
the software, and that would be good
enough. We're here because requirements
change. And I agree, it's actually a
good thing because there's so few of us
and so many of them. So, the more
requirements would change, the better
off we're all going to be. The other
problem is that The reason you're
laughing is because
if you design against the requirements,
and the requirements actually change,
then that inflicts a horrendous pain and
a horrendous cost because now your
design have to change. And once, post
factum, once you already have developed
the system and deployed it, if you
change the design, that is the most
expensive thing you can possibly have.
That sounds very painful. Every new
requirement means uh significant change
across existing components or possibly
even the creation of new components
every time there's a new requirement. Is
that basically what you're saying?
That's the typical situation where you
design against the requirements.
And so,
developers, managers, and so on have
literally learned nowadays to resent the
changes of requirements because that
inflicts pain, and nobody likes pain.
Now, the solution is so simple. It has
eluded most of my entire career, which
is don't design against the
requirements.
Now, it sounds so absurd when I say it,
and you actually laugh, but I'm I'm dead
serious, right? Unless you like pain. If
you like pain, keep doing it. Keep doing
it. It's just fine.
So, the question is what should you do?
And so, the mission of the architect is
to identify the smallest set of building
blocks that you can put together to
satisfy all requirements. That's the
mission.
Now,
I really mean all when I'm saying all.
All requirements, known and unknown,
present and future. Any curveball
anybody could ever throw at you, you can
handle.
Now, this all must be confined within
some sort of parameters, correct? No.
No. No. It's all. All It's all of this.
All All for a particular business, or
all for
okay.
Oh, oh, that's a second. So, now now
we're getting to the gist.
Okay.
So, if you look at most systems Most
systems don't just need to do three
things. They need to do 100 things, 200
things, 300 things, right? Lots and lots
of requirements.
The requirements can be expressed
functionally or behaviorally in form of
use cases, but there's a plurality of
them, right? It's not It's not one or
two or three.
So, if you have 300 things to do, or 300
requirements, it turns out that most
requirements most functionalities are
actually not distinct and unique. Most
requirements are variation of other
requirements.
Most use cases are variation of other
use cases. We have the happy case, the
sad case, the incomplete case, the case
where you're just doing what customer
over there will pay the extra.
So, let's actually define two types of
use cases. There's core use cases and
fluff.
Core use cases represent the essence of
the business. That's what brings the
customer to the door.
Fluff is what
is is all the other things. It turns out
that
all business systems have
a a very small number of core use cases.
I encourage now the listeners to do a
mental exercise
and go and count in their head the
number of truly distinct things their
system is supposed to do.
And most of you will come up with one,
two, maybe three. And
we find the number two or three to be
very typical. We find the number four
and five to be very high. And I've only
seen six once. And by I'm saying I've
seen six six once, I mean it was a
system designed for one of the largest
companies in the world, a company that
every one of the listeners has its
product at home. For a system that is
actually a system of systems supporting
the entire IT infrastructure,
it had 40 services and it was supporting
120,000 users 24/7 in five continents.
You know, okay, then you know what, then
you get six core use cases. Most systems
have a very low number of core use
cases.
I've lost count of how many system we
design at IDesign. It's in the many
hundreds. We have never seen
more than six. And like I said, six has
only happened once.
Typically, the number is two or three,
maybe four. So, it's not a very large
number.
What the architect needs to do is
identify the smaller set of building
blocks. And again, those building blocks
encapsulate some areas of volatility
that you can put together to satisfy all
of the core use cases.
Since all use cases are variation of the
core use cases,
what they actually represent is
therefore a different interaction
between
your building blocks, not a different
decomposition thereof. So, now when the
requirements change, your design does
not.
And this is a fundamental observation.
And I call this whole approach
composable design. You never design
against the requirements. You want to
come up with a smaller set of building
blocks that you can put together to
satisfy
all of the use cases. Now, remember, the
core use cases represent the essence of
the business. The essence of the
business hardly ever changes, and if it
does change, it changes at tectonic
pace, meaning it's really, really slow.
Uh Federal Express is in the business of
shipping packages. It could move move
into ballistic missile control, but not
instantly and maybe never.
Possible, but not plausible. And if
possible, incredibly unlikely and very
slowly.
And so,
by focusing on addressing the core use
cases and have the smaller set of
building blocks that you can satisfy all
the core use cases with,
now when the requirements change, what
changes is the fluff, it's not the core.
And therefore, all it expresses itself
is a different interaction between your
building blocks, not a different
decomposition thereof. So, now when the
requirements change, your design does
not. Okay? That is a fundamental
observation about the design of things.
There's plenty of examples. For example,
the
design of the human body was complete
200,000 years ago, meaning Homo sapiens
appeared 200,000 years ago. Now, I'm
pretty sure that being a software
architect wasn't part of the spec at the
time. And yet, I'm quite capable of
being a software architect. Now,
for most developers and architects, that
would be a contradiction because how
could you possibly have exactly the same
design as a hunter-gatherer and yet
survive as an architect? Most people
would do functional decomposition. They
would design against the requirements.
If they were to design somebody like me,
there would be a box in me for
everything I need to do. There would be
a box
conduct
a conference session, write a book,
drive to the airport, mow the lawn, kiss
the wife, all the things I need to do.
And yet, I don't have a box in me called
be a software architect or write a book.
And yet, I'm using exactly the same
components as a hunter-gatherer. And the
reason is, while I'm using exactly the
same components as a hunter-gatherer,
I'm putting them together in a different
way. And incidentally, the core use case
hasn't changed. And there's just one
core use case, which is survive. That's
the only use case that I need to
actually support. Everything else is
fluff. You look at your immune system.
There's near infinite possible
pathogens, bacteria, and viruses that
could infect you and and kill you. And
your body cannot have an infinite number
of antigens to actually go and fight it.
So, how does it actually work? Your
immune system has a small number of
components. It recognizes
the invasion, composes quickly the
correct response to it,
and treats it.
Everything is done this way. Now,
when I have actually said before, I said
that
you need to come up with a smaller set
of building blocks. That's actually a
very key observation. You have to come
up with a smaller set.
And the reason it has to be small is
because in general, less is more. You're
not in the business of doing more work,
in the business of doing less work.
You want to get away with a smallest
number of building blocks, smallest
number of lines of code, smallest number
of everything.
Now, if I give you a requirement spec
with 300 building blocks in it, I could
have a design that has 300 blocks in it.
Well, that's as we discussed before, a
really bad design.
And I can also come up with a design
that has just one giant god block that
does everything. Well, we've learned the
hard way that's not a good design.
So, somewhere between 1 and 300 is the
smallest possible number. It turns out
that that number if if we try and
guestimate what that number is, we can
use order of magnitude. It's more like
1, 10, 100, 1,000.
And I think everybody recognizes that
number is more like 10 than it is like
100. So, in orders of magnitude, it's
more like 10. It could be 12, it could
be 20, it could be 13, but it's closer
to 10 than it is to 100. And the reason
it's closer to 10
is because
if the way you're supposed to provide
the required behavior of any system, not
just software,
is by
the interaction between those building
blocks,
then fundamentally, you're looking at
how many possible combinations you have.
Now, the number of possible combination
of 10 components is on the order of 10
factorial, which is bazillion as in
Brazilian.
By the time you're talking about 15
factorial, there's enough combinations
here like for every grain of sand on the
planet. And this is even without
discussing partial sets and repetitions.
If I'm allowing that, the number is
truly astronomical. Number of molecules
in the universe. And the number of few
molecules in universe and such.
And so,
three or five components is not enough
because the factorial of three or five
is not high enough. By the time you have
about 10 components, the number of
combination is astronomical. And now,
anything you can throw at it, present
and future, known and unknown, you're
good to go.
And this number, order of about 10, is
another fundamental observation about
the nature of things. For example, if I
were to count how many components are in
my body, I'm not talking about cells,
I'm talking about components. Liver,
kidneys, and so on. It's about 10. And
how many components are in your laptop?
Well, I'm not talking about counting
transistors, I'm counting memory, CPU,
graphic card, network card. Well, it's
about 10. And how many components are in
your car? Engine block, gearbox, water
pump, battery, whatever it is, 10.
Everywhere you look, you're going to
find that number 10. And the reason is
all systems have converged to that
number because no system, even from an
evolutionary standpoint, has any
incentive of having frivolous components
it doesn't actually need.
You only have the smallest possible
number of components that you can
compose together to satisfy all possible
requirements, okay? That's the
fundamental observation about how you
design complex systems. You actually
have very similar components so that you
can have near infinite possible
interactions.
Now, all of that leads to somewhere
else.
If you have a small number of
components, themselves fairly simple,
then suppose something changes. Suppose
something changes in the business
domain. Well, all you have to do is you
don't change the components, you just
change the way you put them together and
you respond quickly to change.
But Jeff, let me ask you a question.
Isn't the ability to quickly respond to
changes in the marketplace and in the
business domain the essence of agility?
Yes, and it sounds like what every
software company would wish for and
every business for that matter.
Every software company wishes for, every
business is craving
and yet almost every software system is
failing to deliver because of design
against the requirements. And so, it is
almost diabolical. They try and respond
quickly to the requirements by doing
functional decomposition. Here's the A,
here's the B, here's billing, here's
invoicing. And by doing so, they
absolutely guarantee the lack of
agility.
Because when a change happened, they
detonate. It's diabolical.
So, how do our listeners begin to turn
the requirements that they're given,
which I imagine from my experience and
theirs as well are often suboptimal? How
do they begin to turn those requirements
into what you describe as core use
cases? So, you may have heard something
I never said.
I said don't design against the
requirements. I didn't say you should
ignore the requirements. Absolutely. You
need them.
Requirements are very important.
Yes, you need them.
Requirements is where you identify the
areas of volatility and the core use
cases.
Yes. So, you have to invest in
requirement analysis.
As a result, this of course takes longer
than functional decomposition.
Functional decomposition Sure,
transcribe it to a user story, tack it
on the Kanban board and away you go.
I'm not saying you should do that.
Do that eventually. Absolutely. If you
want to do the
process artifacts,
then sure, do it. But you're doing it
using the building blocks of composable
design
which encapsulate volatility, right?
Everything has to be in place before you
can actually even do the first attempt
of doing it.
And it includes of course
looking at the requirements. And in the
book I describe a set of analysis tools
of identifying these areas of
volatility. And I describe a set of
techniques and postures even that you
can actually put yourself in
to make it easier to come up with these
areas of volatility because remember,
nobody would ever have a conversation
with you on requirement that sounds like
this. Oh, we're going to change this.
We're never going to change that. We're
definitely going to change this. Nah,
we're not going to change that. They're
only going to talk to you about
functionality and features. That's the
only conversation you're ever going to
have.
And so, what you need to do is take all
of that input in. It's very important.
But then start discerning and prying out
of it the areas of volatility and the
core use cases.
The downside is that it takes longer
than functional decomposition. And
you're going to have to do it under fire
because nobody understand these things.
Everybody wants to get their features
out. You're literally going to have to
be fighting insanity because again,
they're all going to be hell-bent on
doing it wrong, guaranteeing the pain.
It has never worked before. They're
going to hold hell-bent on doing it
again. Okay? Just like alchemy. And so,
the trick is therefore not just doing
it. That's not good enough. Cuz if it
takes you years to do it right, you're
not going to get years.
The trick is actually to do it
effectively and proficiently, quickly.
And in order to do that, you have to
have a lot of practice doing it. So, you
still don't violate the first law of
thermodynamics because you have to sweat
enormously to get to that level of
proficiency and professionalism that you
can do it quickly.
Okay? So, you don't violate the law. You
just don't sweat when it's time to
actually do it.
And that's the essence of true mastery.
You know, and there's a saying that
under fire, everybody sink to their
level of training.
If you try and figure out these things
under fire,
you're just not going to be very good.
Sun Tzu said that winners win and then
they go and fight.
And that's the position you need to be
at. So, that's
I wish I I wish I could promise the
listeners
just a magic bullet. Oh, just one to say
do it my way is a bing zabong, you'll be
fine. It doesn't work this way. This in
fact is the hallmark of quacks. Quacks
promise you an easy win.
No, there's no easy wins here. And you
mentioned before that you're not
proposing a silver bullet, but if
anything it sounds like this is a
rigorous engineering discipline where
you're breaking down the problem into a
composable design where each element of
the design
it encapsulates those areas of
significant change or volatility, and
it's putting them together that causes
the features and the requirements to be
addressed.
Exactly right. Exactly right.
But, you know, is it instant to be a
good engineer? It takes training, takes
education, takes practice.
Takes mentoring, takes practice, right?
Is it Is it Look, our basic expectation
of professionals, be it engineers or
doctors or lawyers or pilots,
is that well-versed, they know their
trade by heart, and that they've
practiced relentlessly to be very good,
right? The last thing you want to do is
be patient number one of a doctor, okay?
And nobody would really want to fly with
a pilot
that just learned how to maneuver
correctly, right? That's not a good
idea, right? You want to fly with
somebody that has tons of hours, okay?
That's a good place to be at.
Absolutely. And that reminds me of
something I've heard of before called
the 2% problem, which is you can never
be good at something that you spend 2%
or less of your time on.
That's something that I I coined the 2%
problem.
Did you coin that?
You kidding me? OF COURSE.
That's hilarious.
So, now the architect has designed these
components, and each of these components
is encapsulating some area of
volatility, but I can almost hear the
product managers and the other managers
saying, "Where are my features?"
So, it turns out that features are
always and everywhere aspect of
integration, not implementation.
It's a universal design rule.
And it is a fundamental observation
about the nature of the universe again,
which what makes it a universal design
rule. So, so what I mean by that?
If you look at the podcast
right now,
if you need to provide a feature called
a podcast, where is the podcast? Is it
in the microphone? Is it
in the keyboard, in the screen, in the
laptop? You cannot point at any one
thing and say, "That's where the podcast
is."
You have to integrate the laptop, the
microphone,
the
streaming devices, the servers. All of
that has to be integrated to get the
podcast.
There's never a box you can say, "Huh,
that's where the podcast is."
You have to integrate things. Okay, so
now let's look say at my laptop, which
I'm using to record this podcast.
The laptop actually doesn't know that
there is a podcast.
The laptop only needs to send to your
server now some kind of audio signal.
So, as far as the laptop is concerned,
there is one feature here, which is send
an audio signal. That's it.
However, there is nothing in the laptop
itself that actually
provides that. I have to integrate the
CPU
where
the calculation is done. I have to
integrate some files for running the
operating system. And I have to
integrate the sound card. And all of
these things have to be integrated to
send you the sound. There is no one box
in the laptop that says send sound.
Okay?
Mhm. So, I mentioned say the hard drive.
The hard drive is storing a bunch of
data required for it. But the hard drive
doesn't actually know
about sending files and sending sound.
The
The hard drive is providing a feature of
storing stuff.
So, as far as the hard drive is
concerned,
the
feature is storing. Okay? So, if you
look at how the hard drive is done, is
there any one thing in the hard drive
that's doing storing? The answer is no,
because the hard drive itself has little
memory chips, and it has a small box
that it has a little screws that's
holding some kind of media. It has some
power regulators and so on.
Okay. So, if I look at the little screw
that's holding the frame of the hard
drive together,
it does nothing about storing files. As
far as the screw is concerned, the screw
is providing one feature, which is
fastening things.
But, is there one thing in the screw
that's doing the fastening? No.
You have to integrate the stem of the
screw and the threads of the screw and
and the head of the screw and the torque
to get the feature of fact of fastening.
Now, you can drill this way all the way
down to the quarks, and you will never
see a feature.
Interesting. So, basically, what you're
saying is Well, actually, what that
brings to mind is a fractal that's
self-similar at all the layers.
where every layer in a fractal provide
its feature as an aspect of integration,
but never implementation, because you
can never actually implement a feature.
You always offer the feature as an
aspect of integration, not
implementation. So, the screw seems like
a really helpful concrete example there,
because the screw itself does not have
the feature called fastening, and yet
the nature of the way the screw is
designed in conjunction with the
the threading that you screw it into,
it's that integration of those two parts
that provides you the feature of
fastening two things together. Is that
correct? That's what you're saying?
Yes, and again, we we now we're zooming
out. If you look at the hard drive,
there's this a thing in the hard drive
doing the storage after integrate the
screw, the media, the power regulator,
the box. All of that is to mitigate it
to the storage.
And if you look at the level of the
laptop, there isn't a single box in the
laptop doing presentation or sending an
audio file. You have to integrate the
graphic card, the CPU, the hard drive,
the bus, the memory to do that.
And you keep going like this. Mhm. So,
you mentioned before that idea of I'll
just summarize it and call it the law of
10, that in every system there tends to
be about an order of magnitude of 10
components, but as we're drilling down,
and maybe this was a question in
listeners' minds before, as we're
drilling down, we're probably finding
another layer within each of those
individual components of 10 order of
magnitude of 10 at the next level. And
then if you drill down into one of those
That's right. And at some point you
reach the standard model of quarks,
which last time I checked is 22 things
in it, which is also order of 10, okay?
Mhm.
Absolutely. Now, it it's architects, we
don't actually deal with quarks or with
screws. At as architects, we actually
deal with overall system architecture,
okay? Where these things are far more
concrete and discernable and and and not
as granular as individual screws, right?
So, but I'm just showing you that
everything in the world is actually put
together this way. Yeah, that makes
sense.
can go up or down and you will never
actually see a feature.
Well, this is some heavy stuff and I
think our listeners are going to have a
lot of questions and possibly desire to
explore more deeply. So, as we're
wrapping things up, is there anything
else we missed that maybe you'd like to
mention in the time we have left?
Yes, what's coming next.
So, as soon as you design the system
without losing a heartbeat, you must
design the project to build it. Mhm.
It doesn't matter how good is your
design,
if you don't have enough time or money
or if the project is too risky, you will
fail to deliver
the system.
So, just as you have to design the
system, you have to design the project
to build it.
And it may come as a complete shock to
you to learn that people are doing it
wrong. And you can make exactly the same
argument about
system design and project design that
you should never do what they're doing
today in project, but instead you should
do something else. And we can have a
whole different podcast on how to design
projects.
And I imagine that just how you had some
opinions about how to
improve on system design, there are also
approaches and techniques for learning
how to correctly do project design.
That is very true.
you said, as we're in the interest of
time, we'll have to move on and leave
that at that. But thank you so much for
your time. And if people want to find
out more about what you're up to, where
are some places they can get more
information?
They can always go to
writingsoftware.org
and learn more about the book or buy the
book.
And hopefully
at some point we're also going to start
and because like like you said, these
ideas are hard to come to terms with,
hard to wrap your head around.
And so we may be we're considering
launching a series of book clubs, which
going to be guided reading by us at
IDesign of the ideas in the book. Okay.
So, that's writingsoftware.org
spelled r i g h t i n g, putting right.
writingsoftware.org Writing up the
industry, exactly right. Okay.
Well, you Well, thank you very much for
joining me to discuss your book Writing
Software. It's been a fascinating
discussion.
Thank you, Jeff. See you next time. This
is Jeff Doolittle for Software
Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
Developers, take your marks. It's time
to upgrade your data platform to
InterSystems IRIS. It's time to deliver
complex mission-critical applications in
the fastest route possible. It's time to
use any data from any source. It's time
to embed analytics and create
interactive user interfaces. So, what
are you waiting for?
Choose your language. Choose your tools.
Choose your environment. Collaborate,
build faster, and deploy more
efficiently. Done and done.
Tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today. InterSystems IRIS
Data Platform, the fastest way to build
applications.
Ready?
Set. Code. Start coding for free.
Visit intersystems.com/try
to try IRIS.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
se-radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5.
Thanks for listening.